2. Lecture

Joe Hartman smiled to himself. This was the place he loved the most. He was wandering confidently in front of his students in the great lecture hall of MIT’s Stata Center, stopping for effect occasionally. Hartman, in his early forties, was the kind of guy who seemed to become more handsome with age, according to most of his female—and also some male—colleagues. It showed that he was hitting the gym regularly to stay in shape. He preferred casual but sophisticated clothing with a European touch.

However, as he liked to put it, it was not his good looks that drew students to his lectures. He was an entertaining speaker who ensured that AI and cryptography remained popular subjects at MIT’s CSAIL, where he had been a tenured professor for the last three years.

His eyes scanned the red seat rows, momentarily stopping at faces to build rapport with his audience. Standing at the front of the room, he sought out students he could connect with to ensure he had their attention. Occasionally, he paused a little longer, hoping to elicit a smile from an attractive face. Today, luck was on his side; a beautiful, petite blonde student with bright, intelligent eyes was sitting in the first row. Their eyes locked in a way that suggested both might be interested in some extracurricular activities.

Joe enjoyed his lecture and was already anticipating his favorite part, which never failed to stir emotions. He paused, opened his arms as if he were about to deliver a sermon, and proclaimed, “It’s safe to say that artificial intelligence has surpassed humanity at this point. Only fools trust people more than machines today! Remember this if you have to make an important decision: Trust the data because data is the truth!”

He looked around expectantly. Joe was excited for a lively debate in class, but something was disturbingly wrong. The students had become agitated, but not in the way he had anticipated.

They were pointing fingers at their screens, and some of them appeared genuinely surprised while wearing their smart glasses. Their vacant look focused on the distance was unsettling for close onlookers, even after many years of the technology being commonplace. Hartman hated it when the attention in his lectures was stolen by the augmented reality overlays, but banning smart glasses from lectures was a fight lost several years ago.

“Hey, what’s going on, guys?” Joe asked while the murmurs and occasional shouts grew louder, spreading like wildfire. He was becoming increasingly irritated by the unexpected turn of events. He stepped forward while his watch started buzzing. Strange, he thought, as it was set to not disturb him with alerts.

The guy sitting next to the pretty girl in the front row held his tablet for Joe to see. It was a stream of chaotic scenes. Cars wreaking havoc on a busy street, like in a bad movie. Things were pretty chaotic, with fire, smoke, and debris flying everywhere. Joe shook his head. “So, let me get this straight: someone made an AI reel, and now all of you are going crazy, or what?”

“It’s all over the news, professor! This is happening, for real!” exclaimed the blonde student. Another student started sobbing, “I was video chatting with my brother in Georgetown when it went down. I saw exactly what he saw, and now he’s offline. Fuck!”

Hartman tapped on his watch. The alert had been a priority message that confirmed the death and destruction he had seen on the screens. The blood drained from his face, and he felt shaky. Barely audible, Joe muttered “Class dismissed” to himself as his students already scrambled out of the room, leaving him alone with his thoughts.

6. Briefing

It was still dark outside when FBI agents Alex Mercer and Jake Lin were waiting for the briefing, each with a cup of too-thin coffee. Mercer’s eyes briefly rested on the large display on the wall, which showed the black and golden Washington Field Office logo with the stylized Capitol, amongst other landmarks, the bold letters WFO in the center, and next to it, the FBI crest.

“Agonizing about that logo again, Mercer?” Jake, his partner, asked, noticing his slight frown.

Mercer, a former Army Ranger, couldn’t help but find the WFO logo more fitting for a sightseeing agency than law enforcement. But it was a minor annoyance compared to other challenges of civilian life he had to navigate in the last years after leaving the army.

“Nah, it’s about what we’ll get to listen to. I heard that we’ll get a lecture about AI instead of doing our work.”

“You mean that Hartman character? Uh-huh, that’s going to be really entertaining. But then again, we’re talking about autonomous cars killing people in the streets, so if he can shed some light on what went wrong with their little silicone brains, it might actually be helpful.”

“I doubt that, Jake,” Mercer said as he scanned the bustling room, filling with agents and officers from various agencies, including some suits he couldn’t place.

As Assistant Director in Charge Helen Koop stepped up to the lantern, the noise died in the room. “Alright, ladies and gentlemen, let’s get going,” Koop said as she started the presentation. After the current statistics of death and destruction were shown in clean and cold figures, a 3D simulation of the events augmented with real footage followed, leaving more than one participant with stirred emotions.

“Looks more like a suicide attack in some hellhole than Boston,” Mercer said, carefully registering all the details.

“We have Professor Joseph Hartman, PhD, from MIT here, who will give us additional information on AI-related aspects. Doctor Hartman and his team developed the Flexible Logistics Optimization and Wayfinding System that coordinates the autonomous cars in most major cities.”

“Well, that worked pretty well, obviously,” Mercer said to Lin as Joe went to the lectern.

“Thank you, Assistant Director. Ladies and gentlemen, let me clarify some aspects of our situation here. For starters, every theory I have seen on social media is just plain wrong,” Joe started his expert statement.

“At least the guy has no problems with his self-confidence,” Lin noticed, which made Mercer chuckle.

After a twenty-minute tour of the de force, from viruses to solar flares causing a malfunction, Joe came to an end and asked, “Any questions?”

Mercer raised his hand: “And what about the obvious, doctor? What about your system? Could it just have steered the cars in the wrong direction?”

“Well, Agent …”

“Mercer”

“Agent Mercer, it’s not my system, and actually, it’s much more than that. FLOWS is a very capable AI designed to prevent accidents, not cause them. But it’s a valid question: Why did the cars do what they did with the system in place?”

“I’m glad you appreciate my question,” Mercer responded with a slightly ironic undertone, “but then, where do we find the answer to that question?”

“It’s in the data, Agent Mercer. But I’m pretty sure you will find human error as the source, not an AI failure.”

“Thank you, Professor Hartman, for your valuable insights. And that’s exactly what we’re going to do,” Koop stepped in. “SENTINEL has been updated just yesterday with extensive new training data sets.”

Mercer rolled his eyes at the mention of the FBI’s investigative AI. “That’s exactly what we need: AIs investigating AIs,” he said to Jake, who silently nodded.

“So, with the new training data, we can be sure that we have a 99.9% unbiased response,” Koop said, addressing a point that has been a problem with such systems from their beginning. AIs respond based on their training data, so any biases or errors in the data are carried over to their reasoning. For example, if there is a high conviction rate among a certain group of people, the AI would tend to see members of this group as more likely to be a suspect.

“We’ll let SENTINEL crunch the data and see what we get,” Koop concluded.

Mercer watched Hartman and Koop leave the room with the other brass as the meeting ended.

“That was just a ton of bullshit, Jake.”

“You mean the good doctor? Yeah, a pretentious asshole, that one.”

“Couldn’t agree more, partner, but I’m more worried about the data crunching part. I wouldn’t be here today if I had always listened to the so-called experts. I'd probably be coming home in a casket with a flag on it.”

“But you aren’t in some forsaken part of the world anymore fighting jihadists, Alex. You heard Koop, this is modern police work.”

Mercer’s jaw tightened. “Trust me, Jake, your instincts will save lives, including yours. Not those fancy algorithms.”

“And there’s truth,” Lin said as they left the briefing room.

While waiting for Koop to finish with the other senior officials, Joe studied the WFO logo on the wall. He was always interested in aesthetics, and from a design perspective, he found it uncomfortably crude.

With a frown, he turned to the Assistant Director as she walked over to him.

“So, Doctor Hartman, thank you for narrowing the field today. We need to put our efforts into the most promising explanations here. The public pressure is mounting, and even POTUS is preparing to address the nation.”

“What message is the President going to deliver?” Joe asked, genuinely wondering himself.

“It’s about the trust in the systems, Doctor. But who am I telling this to? The country basically runs on AI, traffic, law enforcement, hospitals, and even the military. Have you seen the stock market’s reaction to yesterday? The SEC suspended technology stocks until tomorrow when the markets became too volatile. There are billions at stake here.”

“That’s a very good point. And most of the trading is also done by robots today, so there is that.”

Joe briefly wondered what the situation had done to his pension funds, but his train of thought was interrupted by the Assistant Director, who produced a slim silver memory pack from her jacket.

“Let me follow up on your point about finding the answers in the data. As I said, our forensic systems are currently running the analytics, but honestly, we haven’t seen any results yet. Maybe some glitch in the system after the upgrade. Anyhow, this is a complete data dump of all relevant systems. I’m told we’re talking about a few petabytes. It would even be more if the car’s memories hadn’t been wiped by the EMP.”

She held the device out to Joe, who hesitated to take it, his hands resting in his pants’ pockets.

“I’m not sure how I can help you with that.”

Helen Koop looked at him quizzically. “Well, I’m asking you to look into the data yourself. I’m sure you have some quantum supercomputers at MIT that put our humble systems to shame. And maybe notice things we overlook. It’s your area of expertise, if anything.”

With a sigh, Joe took the memory pack from Koop’s hand. “Well, I’ll see what we can do, Ms Koop. But it’s not like we have forensic tools on our servers, so no promises. Sorry,” Joe said, dropping the device in his light black day pack, which he was carrying casually over one shoulder.

“Thanks for trying anyway, Mr. Hartman. Remember, we need quick answers. Safe travels back to Boston!”

After they said their goodbyes, Assistant Director Koop replayed the conversation in her head. It was a bit strange, she thought, that the professor seemed less than enthusiastic about looking into the data - after his passionate statement just a few minutes ago in the briefing room.

10. Melee

Joe Hartman drank the rest of his early morning cappuccino in the kitchen. It was as minimalistic as the rest of his apartment, except for the Italian coffee machine that looked considerably more complicated than the smaller polished steel appliances that adorned the white and grey kitchen unit. Joe was not much of a cooking person himself. He preferred pre-made functional food that contained all amino acids, vitamins, and other nutrients in a well-balanced, personalized formula. Still, he fell in love with Italian coffee while spending a few months on an AI fellowship program at the Politecnico di Milano, one of Italy’s leading technical universities.

Despite a fitful night, his spirits were high, and he looked forward to seeing Emily Stone again. Her message was a welcome surprise, and he quickly agreed to meet her in person to discuss the car incident. That was typical for Emily, taking the trip from Washington to Boston to chat, for which most people would use a video call or a holo-conference. But she always preferred the real world over digital tools, something that contrasted her job as a technology journalist in a way that Joe found adorable, at least with some distance now. His feelings towards her were complicated, to say the least, but deep inside, he felt a strong desire to be with her - even if it was only for a background talk about autonomous cars.

Hartman took his daypack from a chair and checked himself in the mirror. He smiled. The sun was shining, and Joe was sure this would be a great day.

Joe’s apartment was on the second floor of the old brick-stone building on 125 Salem Street, which also hosted an Italian restaurant that would not open until noon. Years ago, when the narrow street was remodeled into a cafe zone, the parking spaces in front had been converted into an outdoor seating area. For Luke Brennan, Spartan One, this meant that a quick snatch of the professor without too much public attention wouldn’t be feasible when Hartman left his building. They would have to follow him along until a better opportunity presented itself.

“Spartan One, Spartan Four,” Brennan heard the voice of Jeremy Hanson, one of his team, over the earpiece.

“Go for Spartan One,” Brennan answered while scanning the street around him, a few meters north of Hartman’s apartment on the corner of Prince Street.

“Target is on the move, approaching your pos.”

“Understood, Five, keep eyes on the target. All other callsigns converge on my pos, nice and slow.”

Alex Mercer and Jake Lin were sitting with two other agents from the Boston Field Office in an unmarked black SUV on Hanover Street less than two hundred yards away. While Jake was watching the pedestrians moving on the sunny sidewalk, Alex was focused on the tablet that showed several camera views of Salem Street. The plan was simple: Follow the suspect after leaving his apartment and arrest him on the street. Alex would have preferred to raid Hartman’s apartment last night and frog-march him away in his pajamas. Still, the BFO feared social media streams showing the FBI going Rambo in the lively Little Italy neighborhood. It was beyond Mercer why an arrest on the open street in the morning should be any more discreet. Still, Hartman’s personality analysis provided by SENTINEL indicated that he would not resist any public police action to save his face, so the decision was made. And maybe citizen journalists slept in, Mercer thought and chuckled softly.

“We have a fix, boys,” Mercer called out. A male in his 40s, wearing glasses and carrying a black day pack over his shoulder, was showing up on his tracking app, leaving 125 Salem Street. A red rectangle appeared over his face with the information “Hartman, Joseph R.—Arrest warrant active. Proceed with extreme caution.” in bold type right next to it.

“He’s on his way up north. Get us rolling, Jake!”

While Joe was strolling up the street with upbeat music in his ears, he read the latest news in his smart glasses. He was used to dividing his attention between the world around him and whatever he watched with his glasses, and for what it was worth, every smart glass featured a collision detection algorithm that would warn him of any obstacles the glasses’ cameras captured.

So he was more than surprised when he noticed a strong hand on each of his shoulders. He spun around and saw two men right next to him.

“Doctor Hartman, we would like to have a word with you,” an athletically built man in dark cargo pants and t-shirt appeared before him. His face was obscured behind a full brown beard and dark shades.

“What the fuck?” Mercer muttered as he saw three bodies converge on Hartman on his tablet. The tracking AI couldn’t identify them yet, so a grey rectangle appeared around them, labeled Contact 1, 2, and 3. Hartman seemed to be ignorant of the situation.

“Overwatch, Mercer. We have a development here,” Mercer called Edwards, sitting in the e-chopper again, hoovering above the AO.

“I see it, Mercer, and I don’t like it. Get your asses over there!”

“You heard the man. Move, move, move!” Mercer shouted while the SUV’s doors were already flying open, disgorging four men in blue windbreakers, the bold yellow letters FBI widely visible on their backs.

Joe yanked off his smart glasses, irritated by the sudden approach. “What do you want from me? Who the hell are you?”

“Somebody wants to talk to you, Hartman, and we are the ones to make sure you make it to your appointment,” Luke Brennan said while looking Joe straight in the eye.

“I… don’t understand?!” Joe’s mind raced. One thing was sure: those guys weren’t friends of Emily, and they didn’t look like FBI either. Mugging on the open street was also unlikely with all the CCTV cameras around them. They knew exactly who he was, so something completely different was happening. But what?

Out of the corner of his eye, he saw movement. Looking behind the man blocking his way, he saw four figures running in his direction.

“Gotta move, Hartman,” Brennan said as the two other guys behind him grabbed his arms. Joe always took pride in his functional fitness training, but their grip remained strong as he tried to free himself. He struggled as his smart glasses flew onto the pavement and were crushed under the hiking boots of one of his assailants. A black van pulled up beside them on the street, and the men started to drag Hartman in its direction.

“Freeze, FBI!” Lin shouted as they closed the distance to Hartman and the three men who tried to kidnap the suspect.

Brennan turned in their direction and quickly evaluated the situation. His orders were clear, but he didn’t like the odds of this confrontation. It was a matter of seconds until other agents would appear on the scene.

“Two, Four, set him free,” he ordered Hanson and Mendez, Spartan Two, who had nearly wrestled Joe into the car.

Joe was relieved to be let go, the adrenaline pumping through his system. The FBI agents stopped and held their guns at the group; one of them pointed at him. “What’s going on, for fuck’s sake?” Joe cried out. He was even more confused when he realized that this was the agent he argued with yesterday, Mercer.

“Joseph Hartman, you are being placed under arrest on suspicion of multiple murders!”

The world started spinning around Joe. The situation was unreal. Pedestrians stopped in their tracks, capturing the scene on their smart glasses and phones and undoubtedly streaming it in real-time.

Brennan spoke softly but clearly through his team’s earpieces: “We need the target off the scene. Three, stun them.”

“Hey, you, stop the fuck talking,” Lin shouted in Brennan’s direction but noticed at the same moment a metallic clatter when something flew out of the van on the sidewalk. “Grenade!” he yelled in horror when he realized what he had just seen. The agents dived down to the ground.

With a bright flash and a loud boom, the M-84 grenade went off, filling the street with dark smoke. The operatives, protected by their smart glasses and noise-canceling earpieces, used the moment of disorientation to move toward their car, Brennan grabbing the stunned Hartman by his backpack.

Alex Mercer was the first to shrug off the effects of the flashbang grenade, years of relentless training kicking in. He jumped forward as he saw movement in the thick, acrid smoke. The situation was too chaotic for using his gun, especially with confused civilians around him, so he holstered his Glock and tried to get hold of the nearest kidnapper.

From the corner of his eyes, Brennan saw Mercer coming forward. He showed Joe aside just in time to block a blow aimed at his head. Brennan quickly reacted and countered with a blow of his own that Mercer ducked away by a few inches. Both men locked eyes for a moment.

“What the fuck,” Mercer thought before he realized that another gun was pointed straight at him by one of Brennan’s associates. He slowly raised his arms and waited for what came next. But the shot he expected never came as the three attackers jumped into the unmarked black van that sped away, clipping the pavement and barely missing a pair of onlookers.

When Alex Mercer looked around, he saw the other agents moving around with drawn guns, looking for targets and police cruisers rushing to the scene. His eyes scanned the scenery for new threats. The confrontation lasted only a few seconds but took some precious moments to process.

He had the feeling he was missing something important.

“Where the fuck is Hartman?”

14. Travel

After they said their goodbyes, Joe Hartman was on the move again, wary of being recognized by cameras or cops. So, he kept his routine of avoiding both whenever possible.

Despite his efforts, after a few minutes, he felt watched. He slowly turned to the other side of the street, where a bearded man in a black hoodie and dark blue jeans stood. The man looked around suspiciously and spoke to somebody, likely over his dark-tinted smart glasses. Joe began to sweat. A robotaxi turned the corner and stopped next to the bearded stranger. Just as Joe prepared to break into a run, the man opened the passenger door of the cab, and an elderly grey-haired woman emerged. Both embraced, and Joe let out the breath he had held in a sigh.

After the bearded man’s encounter proved innocuous, Joe’s heart rate finally lowered. He decided to improve his disguise, smearing his ball cap, shirt, and already bruised face with muddy water from a puddle. Grabbing a discarded plastic cup, he assumed the role of a homeless person, knowing it was the best way to blend in—people tend to ignore the homeless.

The situation felt surreal. Just an hour ago, he was a respected MIT professor, and now, he was a fugitive dressed as a vagrant, hunted by the FBI and thugs with grenades. He shook his head. But where to go? If he wanted his life back, he needed a place to hide and to work out what had happened in the last 48 hours.

Joe was sure there was always a logical solution to every situation. Ideally, he would find not only a place but also some support. Emily had offered him as much, and if anything positive came out of this mess, she was talking to him again. But he couldn’t go with her in Washington. He was sure the FBI would have her on their radar sooner than later. Their history together was no secret. She’d be better off focusing on her research about the incident as a respected journalist without him hiding in her apartment and causing distractions.

Thinking about it, the ideal place would be remote enough without the city’s omnipresent cameras and with a sharp mind to help unravel this mystery. And nobody was sharper than David Donnelly.

There was still the problem of getting to the remote cabin. What helped him become invisible in the city wouldn’t help him to hitch a ride to rural Maine, and using a robotaxi or any public transportation was out of the question.

When was David leaving for his cabin? Joe tried to remember what David had said when they met in the bar, but he wasn’t sure. He had lost his smart glasses in Salem Street and had no other way to contact David, so the best option was to go to David’s home and see if he was still around.

Joe walked for two hours, carefully avoiding detection by taking numerous detours. His left calf throbbed with pain from the uneven height of his sneakers, but he couldn’t risk adjusting them. When he finally arrived in Somerville, rain began to fall. The street where David lived was lined with quaint, suburban-style houses. He rang David’s bell, but there was no answer. Seeing David’s pickup still in the driveway, he decided to wait but knew he couldn’t linger outside without drawing attention. Exhausted and aching, Joe noticed the truck bed covered with a tarp, the hydro-generator fixed next to the cabin. Desperate for rest, he climbed under the tarp and fell asleep to the rhythmic sound of the rain.

Joe was jerked from his dreamless sleep when David’s truck turned from the driveway into the street. The rain was still pouring heavily, so David entering and starting the truck hadn’t woken him up, but tumbling across the truck’s bed certainly did. With the adrenaline rushing through his veins again, he was suddenly wide awake. He grasped one of the straps David had used to tie down the generator. “David, stop the fucking car!” He yelled, but he had no chance of being heard with the heavy rain and muffled by the tarp. David turned up his car’s sound system and selected the playlist ‘Rock’n’Roots’, with Creedence Clearwater Revival kicking off the soundtrack for the three-hour drive.

When David merged into I-93, Joe had given up on yelling and kicking on the floor to make himself heard. The air streaming over the tarp had replaced the platter of rain. Joe concentrated on keeping himself fixated on the truck’s bed, trying to change his position occasionally to reduce the stress on his joints and muscles.

He had considered jumping out of the truck at the next stop, but he couldn’t know how long David might stop or where. He figured he’d probably get thrown off the bed on the highway and run over by a car behind him, so he forgot about that option. He improvised a makeshift harness using his daypack and the loose ends of the straps that tied down the generator, which provided him with some anchoring.

He was—literally—clinging for his life for what felt like hours, completely losing track of the time he had already endured this ordeal. When the car slowed down and rumpled over a dirt road, Joe was too battered to do anything more than hope that they would soon arrive at their destination.

When the truck finally stopped, Joe barely registered the sound of the engine being turned off and the driver opening the door. He gingerly tried to move his arms and groaned as he worked on the daypack to get out of it. After all the pounding and straining, everything hurt like hell or was numb. He tried again and finally was able to get his right side free with a stifled cry of pain.

He was so focused on getting out of his harness that he was shocked when the tarp was suddenly yanked back: Joe found himself staring down the barrel of a gun for the second time today.

16. Traumatized

On the surface, Maria Hayes looked unscathed by the events in Georgetown. Although she was at the center of the autonomous cars’ killing spree, she was at least physically unharmed. But the trauma she had suffered caused her much pain. She wasn’t able to go out of her apartment again, paralyzed by fear.

“Sweetheart, you need to get out of Washington. Leave that all behind. Come down to Austin. I can help you here,” Rebecca Hayes said to her daughter, who was looking away from her on the screen.

Professor Hayes was the head of the Immersive Learning Lab at the University of Texas in Austin and a trained psychologist. The Lab offered the latest technology in immersive virtual reality. At its core were sensory deprivation tanks with advanced brain projectors. Rebecca knew that those could not only be used for learning new skills but also for unlearning negative memories, reframing them to drain them of their power. The university had several research grants from the DoD and DARPA for training soldiers and investigating new ways to treat Post Traumatic Stress Disorders.

When Maria looked back at her mother, tears rolled down her cheeks.

“When I close my eyes, I see this young man, the fear. And the next second, he was gone.” Maria started sobbing, “I had his blood all over me, mommy.”

Rebecca was a striking woman in her fifties who usually exuded an air of calm professionalism. But now her emotions were clearly visible on her face, although she tried to hide them.

“Honey, let me see when I can get to Washington, and then I take you home with me, okay? You know, the commercial planes are still grounded, but I will find a way, baby.”

“I just want to go home, mommy.”

Rebecca was furious. She had tried to find transportation to Washington for more than an hour without success. The killing car incident led to an immediate and complete shutdown of all vehicles solely operated by AI. Although the ban was soon lifted, the Federal Aviation Administration was the last to allow operations again. Remembering 9/11, this reaction was understandable and probably advisable, but this didn’t help her get Maria back.

Even if train tickets were available, it would take her two days to make the trip. Frustrated, she also considered driving up, but twenty-four hours behind the steering wheel would leave her too exhausted to take care of her daughter, and given her predicament, she couldn’t take Maria back with her in a car.

She swore. Rebecca Hayes wasn’t a violent person, but if she could get hold of those responsible for the killings and the other casualties, she would inflict so much pain on them, by God.

“Just one more try,” she told herself, tapping on her tablet again. She couldn’t believe her luck when a connection to Washington Dulles, tomorrow night, popped up. She said a silent prayer when she tried to book the flight.

Two minutes later, she looked at the ticket in her digital wallet.

“Mommy will be there soon, sweetheart,” she said, thinking about Maria.

21. Waves

Frustrated, Joe Hartman shut the laptop he had been trying to work on with the data dump. He had to admit that he hadn’t made any progress over the last few hours. The memory pack included data from the traffic AI FLOWS, the telemetry streams captured from the cars, and video data from traffic cams in M Street. Its sheer multitude was overwhelming. He typically relied on an AI to analyze the data and work with it, but unfortunately, for many reasons, this wasn’t possible.

He stood from the sofa and walked over to the large bookshelf tucked under the stairwell, the wooden floor creaking softly. Over the years, physical textbooks became pretty uncommon, and their death blow came when search engines evolved into AI-powered conversational interfaces. Ask a specific question and get a tailored answer.

While sitting in their favorite bar, David once explained to Joe pointedly, “When the internet is flooded with AI hallucinations, libraries with paper books will be the only reliable source of information.” Joe also knew that David was not against using digital technology. He was far from it. David loved to work with complex systems but wanted to keep his mind fed with information and inspiration. Joe smiled, remembering this conversation, and took one of the classics, “Artificial Intelligence: A Modern Approach,” from the shelf.

But a thought made him stop thumbing through the well-used volume. Most of the groundbreaking discoveries had been made without artificial intelligence. Actually, it was pen, paper, and hard thinking. He needed no internet for that.

With new-found enthusiasm, he decided to grab something to eat and tackle the data again.

Joe searched through every cabinet in David’s kitchen until he found a can of baked beans. He heated them up quickly and carried the steaming bowl over to the sturdy and well-worn wooden table where he had placed the laptop, a legal pad, and a set of Sharpies that Joe had found while searching for something edible.

He would have to apply first principles thinking here, breaking down complex problems into their most basic, foundational elements and building up from there.

He started by sketching the positions of the involved cars and the victims by reviewing the video feeds. After the first seconds of watching, he dropped his spoon into the bowl and pushed it away; his appetite was gone. Seeing the traffic camera recordings made it feel more real than the flashy videos in the newsfeeds that could as well have been algotrash action movies. People had died that day horribly, and this realization hit Joe with all the power of a sucker punch to his guts.

The images of his parent’s accident that he had kept contained for so long in the back of his mind came back to him with full force, and the emotions nearly overwhelmed him. He needed fresh air.

Joe opened the cabin door and stepped out on the small landing. He leaned back to the wall made of weathered horizontal logs, their colors ranging from dark brown to a faded grey-brown. His hand touched the rough surface of the wall. He closed his eyes and listened to the soothing sounds of the woodland.

But his ears picked up something else—nothing more than a soft whining, an artificial sound that didn’t belong there. He opened his eyes again and tried to locate its source. The dense trees surrounding the cabin made it harder, but he was certain it had come from above. He looked up, but the sound was gone, and there was nothing to see through the leaves. Was it a drone, or was he getting paranoid?

He waited for a couple of minutes, but the noise didn’t return. Maybe it was just one of David’s generators or a water pump. He remembered his encounter with the deer a few hours ago. He shouldn’t panic and get back to work. He looked around once more and walked back into the cabin.

After jotting down the locations of the cars, the victims, and the timestamps of the collisions, he wasn’t sure what he was looking at. It seemed like utter chaos at first sight, but there was something else upon closer inspection.

He looked up the telemetry data of the involved cars to get their exact position and transferred his observations into a table. He reviewed the spreadsheet, scrutinizing each data point meticulously, but nothing stood out. Frustration welled up inside him.

Joe stood up and paced the room, the floorboards creaking under his feet. He started thinking aloud, “Okay, what am I missing? Where’s the pattern?” He stopped by the window, staring into the forest. Maybe it wasn’t about the individual cars but how they interacted with each other.

Returning to the table, Joe decided to visualize the data. He drew a rough grid on the legal pad using the Sharpies, plotting each car’s position and movement. He adjusted the positions multiple times, trying different configurations. He sighed and rubbed his eyes, exhaustion setting in.

He returned to the telemetry data, focusing on the timestamps. Using this, he started a visual simulation of the cars’ movements on his laptop. He slowed down the simulation and smoothed out the time intervals between the collisions.

“Holy shit!” Joe exclaimed when he clearly saw the pattern that his unconsciousness apparently had noticed before. He replayed the visualization again and again, but there was no doubt.

The incident started at one point when two cars converged on one victim and then spread like waves through the other cars involved until they suddenly stopped with the electromagnetic pulse the police officer had used to disable the cars.

There was a victim number zero, and the waves of destruction and death that rippled through M street weren’t random.

Joe’s mind formed a question that could be the start of a thread to unravel the mystery of the incident: Who was victim zero, with whom the killing started?

24. Swarm

Joe Hartman had been reviewing the footage of the traffic and security cameras on the memory pack, searching for Victim Zero, with whom the killing in M Street had started.

It was a gut-wrenching process. He found a young man with curly dark hair whose last minute began with looking into a coffee shop window. It was hard to tell if he was looking for somebody or studying the menu. When the first autonomous car suddenly swerved in his direction, he seemed to react quickly, as if expecting it, and started to run. This moment, somewhere between shock and determination, was caught in the screenshot Joe had made to isolate the face of the man. It wasn’t perfect, but at least most of him was visible. A fraction of a second later, when Joe scrubbed the videos forward, the man was hit by another car coming from the opposite direction. Victim Zero was—Joe was lacking a better word—quashed between the two cars with brute force.

The data dump he had received from the FBI didn’t include any personal information about the victims, only the video and data streams. His only chance to learn more about the first victim was to run his face through face recognition. This would only work if the man had left an image trace on social media. Unfortunately, Joe had no access to the government databases, which were pretty exhaustive since the CIA, NSA, and other three-letter agencies were also sourcing additional information from other countries. But all that was pretty academic, as Joe had no internet access.

It wasn’t exactly a dead end, but this was how far it would go now. He looked at the image of Victim Zero on the screen and asked softly: “What have you done to end this way?”

Joe stood up and stretched his neck to the left and right, which responded with a series of light cracks. Sitting hunched over the keyboard for hours had made his upper body tense. He warmed up the baked beans a second time and added a bag of potato chips from David’s supplies to his meal. With another cup of coffee, he returned to the laptop.

All he had to work with right now was the memory pack, petabytes of data streams, and video files. He had already thoroughly reviewed the videos; now, he turned to the data. Joe rubbed his temples, the weight of the task pressing down on him. He was well aware that this would likely not explain the reason for Victim Zero’s death, at least not directly. So, instead, he focused on how the attack was delivered.

He took a deep breath and started jotting down his next steps while talking to himself:

“First, identify Connections: Extract all data streams from the cars involved in the attack. Look for any shared patterns or anomalies.

“Second, dig Deeper: Check the FLOWS data for any unusual communication between the central AI and the rogue cars.

“Third, spot the Differences: Compare the behaviors of the attacking cars against those that didn’t participate. What made them different?”

He looked out of the window and watched little patches of sunlight dancing on the ground. It wasn’t a very sophisticated plan, but at least it was a plan. Step by step, he would try to solve the mystery behind the attacks that had shocked America and thrown his life into chaos.

Joe's eyes burned from staring at the screen. Hours had passed, and he had checked off all three items on the list one by one. He leaned back in his chair. The results were sobering.

The data streams didn’t show much except that the cars’ AIs had suddenly sped up to crash into the next obstacle, whether it was another car or a pedestrian. But the data didn’t explain why they did this. The FLOWS data was clean; it just documented the central AI’s failed attempt to stop the rampaging cars remotely. Joe opened the simulation of the crashes again. After watching the ripple effect starting at Victim Zero again, he thought about how the spreading of the attacks reminded him of the circular waves you could watch dropping a stone into calm water. Or like dominoes knocking over their neighbors in a domino toppling display.

He nervously tapped with his pen on the table. Why was this happening? There had to be something.

Then it hit him. It wasn’t what was there, but what was missing. The way the malfunction propagated required a medium, a way of passing it from one car to another. If there was no data in the streams that explained this effect, it was either deliberately not tracked or transmitted in a hidden, unknown way.

He opened the cars’ hardware specifications and looked closer at the chipsets used for the onboard AI. “Interesting…” he muttered. All the cars involved in the killings were running on Bold Industries chipsets. This wasn’t a surprise given Bolt’s domination of the market for AI chips, but those were all of the latest generation.

Joe thought back to the evening with David in the bar in Boston, which seemed to be years ago, although it was only three days. They were talking about Jason. Joe was shaking his head when he remembered David saying Bolt’s self-organizing AI concepts were, what was the word now, “intriguing”.

The concept was built on the idea that AI chips in devices like phones, smart glasses, or home appliances could connect on demand without additional hardware to collaborate on complex tasks. Jason had been discussing this idea he called “swarming” with Joe as a potential topic for his PhD thesis years ago, and it was still on a theoretical level. Connecting the chips was difficult due to the necessary connection speed. Even bigger were the security concerns. At the end of the day, this would open a huge backdoor to critical hardware, like payment systems or… cars.

It all clicked. Bold Industries. Swarming AI. Vulnerable systems. “Jesus Fucking Christ,” Joe whispered, the full horror of the situation crashing down on him. The missing data wasn't a coincidence; it was the key. This was only the beginning.

26. Killian Court

Emily Stone and David Donnelly walked slowly through Killian Court, the Great Dome behind them.

“We are being watched. Let’s pretend we are just having a casual chat,” David said, smiling at Emily.

“Yeah, the FBI tracked me down using Logan’s security cameras, and two agents intercepted me at the terminal curb. It’s probably them.”

“Actually, I don’t think that’s FBI we’re dealing with here. I also had a visit by two agents, and the guys following us are from a different team. Joe told you about the ones who tried to kidnap him?”

“You think the kidnappers are after us?” Emily was clearly alarmed, and her voice showed. Her dark hair pulled back in a tight ponytail, and she looked around nervously.

David put a hand on her shoulder and smiled again. “I think we’re safe in the public and the watchful eyes of the campus police. If they had wanted to make their move, they probably would have done so already. More likely, they hope we lead them to Joe.”

Emily frowned. “Please tell me that Joe is okay.”

“The last time I saw him, he was rattled and shaken but ok. Unless he used my Remington to shoot himself accidentally in the foot, he should be safe for now.”

“You gave him a gun?” Emily groaned.

“Well, a pump gun, technically. Remington 870, to be exact.”

Emily closed her eyes and took a deep breath. After exhaling through her mouth, she opened her eyes again. “Let me rephrase, Dave. Why, in God’s name, did you give Joe a pump gun?”

“Bears?”

Emily frowned again, and David quickly added, “Relax, Emily. He’s in my cabin up in Maine. No cameras there, no mobile networks, the wood is dense, so no satellite imagery, and the trees also give the drones a hard time.”

“You know, it’s no wonder you and Joe get along so well.”

“I’m not sure that’s a compliment,” David said with a broad smile.

“Go, figure,” Emily answered but weakly smiled back.

“All right, let’s share some notes, shall we? What did you make of the agents at the airport?”

Emily got the little black notebook from her bag and opened it. “Special Agents Alexander Mercer and Jake Lin. They didn’t ask much, but if I see Joe, I should tell him to contact them for his own sake. I don’t know if that was a good cop, bad cop act, but Agent Mercer seems to have his doubts about their AI coming up with Joe as the suspect.”

“That’s interesting,” David said thoughtfully. “Those two were the same ones who waited for me at home when I returned from the cabin. They asked about Joe’s past and seemed especially interested in his relationship with Jason Bolt.”

“What’s Bolt got to do with the car attacks?” Emily asked.

“That’s a very good question. Maybe Joe has an idea what this was about.”

After a short moment of silence, David smiled again. “The good thing is, I’m fairly sure they had no idea that Joe was hiding in my cabin. But then again, he was traveling there hidden under a tarp on my truck bed, and there was a shitload of rain coming down.”

“Under a tarp. On your truck bed.” Emily repeated slowly and raised her left eyebrow.

“Honestly, you don’t want to know, Emmy.”

“Jesus… Anyways, I’m really glad Joe has a friend like you in this mess,” Emily said and hugged David.

“And like you, Emmy. He needs you as much as me now.”

After a moment of hesitation, she nodded. “And I will be there.”

“Do we have audio, Four?” Luke Brennan asked over the tactical network. Over the last few minutes, they followed Emily Stone and David Donnelly as they walked on Killian Court. They didn’t get much helpful intel from the drone’s video. It had to fly at a high altitude to avoid detection and its small size meant that its cameras and microphones were not designed for high-resolution spying. It was mainly used as a tactical tool to gather information about movement and position, which was still helpful for tracking people in crowded areas, like a park, but not much else.

“Sorry, boss, I can’t get a good fix on them,” Hanson replied.

“Okay, Two, have you got anything for me?”

“It looks like Donnelly said something that agitated Stone, but then they hugged, and everything seems good now,” Marty Decker answered.

“Well, happy to hear it worked out for them,” Brennan said sardonically.

He was quite sure that the two had been conferring about Hartman, and it was nagging him that they hadn’t been able to gather more intel so far.

Brennan had a sinking feeling that Hartman wouldn’t turn up at this meeting, and he had to decide how to proceed with the two targets.

“So, what are our next steps?” Emily asked David.

“We need to dig deeper to find out what Bolt has to do with Georgetown. And I wouldn’t put it past him that he fed the FBI wrong information. There has to be a reason why the Feds asked about Joe’s parents.”

“But wouldn’t that be normal police work? Looking into the personal history of a suspect?”

“But they specifically asked about a childhood trauma, Emmy. We both know his loss drove him to build technology to avoid accidents. It’s quite a stretch to see a line here to become a mass murderer, using cars, of all things.

“And they also asked about Joe’s relationship with Bolt, so Jason is definitely part of the equation here.”

“If we both believe that Joe is innocent and was framed, the question is, who profits from this? My first instinct would be to think of the person or organization responsible for the killing cars. Or…”

“Watch out!” A voice yelled behind them, making both jump in shock.

A soccer ball zipped between them, only to be trapped by a young man running across the lawn from their right side.

Emily needed a moment to calm down before they started walking again.

“You’re the investigative journalist, Emmy. Find a motive to make sense of all of this.”

Emily nodded, took out her phone, and held it up as if to snap a selfie with David.

“Smile!”

However, when she tapped the button on the camera app, she took a picture of the people in front of her instead of the two of them.

“And I’m going to find out who those guys are who have been circling us since we started to walk,” she said, smiling amiably at David.

David’s smile widened. “That’s how we do it! I’m returning to the cabin to see how I can help Joe. But first, we must get rid of the pretty boys you just added to your photo library.”

He looked around and spotted the two campus police officers still on their beat.

“And I think I have a plan.”

“Did she just take a picture of us? That sneaky bitch!” Luke Brennan was swearing under his breath.

“Should we get the phone, One?” Mendez asked his team leader.

“Nah, fuck it, she’ll have it uploaded to the cloud already, so it can be restored anyways, even if we delete it.”

“One, it looks like they approach the campus cops,” the voice of Hanson, Spartan Two, came urgently over the tactical network.

Brennan realized that his covert operation might become less than covert in a few moments and that the General wouldn’t be too happy about more publicity.

“Let’s get some distance between us and them. If they alarm the cops, it’s a tactical retreat,” he ordered his team over the network.

“Excuse me, officers,” Emily smiled sweetly at the unformed campus cops.

The younger of the two smiled back. “How can we help you, ma’am?”

“I was wondering,” she said, turning to her side and pointing vaguely with her right hand toward Brennan and Mendez, “if you could take a picture of us?”

Both officers looked at each other, and the elder cop shrugged. “Sure thing, ma’am,” and Emily handed him her phone.

When Luke Brennan saw Emily presenting her phone to the cops, there was no time to lose. “All Spartan elements, retreat as low-key as possible. Recall the drone. We meet up at our rides,” he spoke softly, turned around, and walked toward Charles River.

“We wait until Donnelly’s car moves again and then follow him. I have the feeling he isn’t going home yet.”

“Ugh, let’s hope the old man is not just driving to his Bingo night,” Decker remarked, bored.

“Never underestimate an old hand like Donnelly, Two,” Brennan said soberly.

“You’re sure this was your guy, this Brennan character?” Jake Lin asked Alex Mercer. “He didn’t show up on the face recognition.”

Brennan lowered his field glasses. “I have expected that much. He and his team are blanked out in the system. They are called covert operators for a reason.”

“Not so covert if you ask me. Even Stone and Donnelly made them.”

Mercer had to chuckle. “They don’t act like the smoothest operators, I give you that. Let’s return to the car and see where our two friends go next.”

Just as the two agents were on their way, Mercer’s phone chimed.

“Okay, this is unexpected,” he said, turning to Jake after seeing who was calling him.

29. Road Trip

“One, Three. Donnelly’s on the move again, northbound. How copy?” Decker asked over the network, hiding behind a large maple tree a few yards from David Donnelly’s driveway.

“Good copy, Three. It matches our tracking signal. Get back to the car; we will be rolling in two mikes,” Luke Brennan answered after looking at Mendez’s tablet with the tracking app.

“Let’s hope we get lucky tonight,” Hanson said enthusiastically from the backseat.

“So do I, Hanson, so do I,” Luke Brennan said without taking his eyes from the moving dot on the tablet.

After an hour on the interstate to Maine, David Donnelly checked his mirrors again for anything suspicious, as he had done every two or three minutes since he left his driveway. The trees and fields sped past, along with the occasional traffic sign, just as they always did on his way to the cabin. But today, he was much more aware of his surroundings than on any other trip before.

When he saw the sign advertising the next service station, he veered to the right and left the interstate.

The parking lot held several pickup trucks like his—a small comfort. In rural America, this type of car was still king. No electric engines, no electronic bells and whistles, just enough horsepower and loading space.

He pulled up next to another dark Dodge Ram, similar to his. Upon closer inspection, it would be obvious that it was a different car, but for his purpose, it would be close enough.

David got out of his pickup and looked around. No surveillance cameras, just as he had remembered, and no other people in sight. He carried the metal box to the other car, every step crunching on the gravel. Gingerly he placed it under the tarp. If his calculations were right, whoever placed the trackers would be not too far away but not too close by to be seen either. Or at least, he hoped so.

“Donnelly has stopped at a service station five clicks ahead of us. Do we go after him, One?” Mendez asked his team leader.

Brennan, still irked by the botched surveillance at Killian Court, sighed. That private investigator shit was a far cry from their usual behind-enemy-lines operations.

“We stop at the next pull-off for five mikes and see if he takes a leak or grabs a coffee and moves on. Speaking of which, unmount and use the time wisely, boys,” Brennan decided.

“Never miss a piss,” Hanson joked, heading for the nearest tree.

David was starting to get nervous. The longer he stayed, the higher the chances that somebody came looking for him and his car, and his bluff would be called.

He was about to retrieve the box when he saw movement—a square-shouldered man in a dark jacket. David started the engine of his truck, ready to make for a run when the hazards of the pickup next to him blinked. Looking over, David saw the man making a beeline for the diver’s door.

He sighed when the truck beside him started moving. David quickly checked the mirrors before following him and blending back into the traffic on the interstate.

Luke Brennan watched the red dot on the screen while they were on their way to the service station.

“He’s moving again. Fall back!”

At the next rest area, David pulled over again. “Time to see if my little ruse has worked,” he said softly. It was a risky decision, but he didn’t want to lead any potential followers directly to his cabin and, consequently, to Joe.

He walked over to an oak tree, from which he had a good view of Interstate 95, and raised his field glasses. He wasn’t sure what to expect, so he watched the passing cars for the next ten minutes. A black SUV could have been what he was looking for, but with the tinted glasses, it was hard to tell anything about the passengers apart from the two severely looking guys in the front seats.

After waiting another 20 minutes and checking his car again for radio signals, he was satisfied enough to start his engine again and make his way to the cabin.

“I really hope this worked,” he mumbled as he turned on his car’s sound system and selected his favorite rock playlist, immediately raising his spirits.

“Where are you heading?” Brennan asked himself as they neared Houlton, still behind Donnelly’s tracking signal.

He opened the secure communication app on his phone and selected Richard Clayton’s contact. The general answered within a few seconds. “Go for Clayton.”

“General, Spartan Actual. Do we have authorization to cross the Canadian border?”

Clayton’s answer was quick, as he had obviously followed the pursuit himself on the tracking app.

“Affirmative, Spartan. Reconnoiter the destination.”

“Roger that, Sir. Do we engage if we identify our target?”

“Avoid hassling the Canucks, Luke. I don’t want any diplomatic incidents. Everything else, use your own judgment.”

“Copy that, sir.”

After the call had ended, Luke Brennan briefly closed his eyes. This operation was getting more annoying by the minute. He really hoped to simplify the situation soon with some good old and honest-to-God fighting.

33. Tavern

Joe Hartman took in the scenery as David Donnelly found a place to park his truck. To his left stood the rustic 'Harbor Tavern' with its dark shingled façade, while the 'Harbor Craft Brewery' to its right had an industrial metal-clad exterior. The sky was dark and clear, making the welcomingly illuminated tavern even more inviting.

David slung the rucksack with his laptop over his shoulder. As both walked up the stairs made of stone to the dark wooden deck in the tavern’s front, the muted live music from the tavern already greeted them. Opening the door, the warm air laced with the smell of food and hops made Joe’s stomach growl. He wondered if they had time to get something warm to eat, eyeing the burgers being served at a table next to him.

They strode to the bar, and David heartily greeted the sturdy man polishing a beer mug.

“Hey there, Hank!”

“Why, good to see ya, Dave! How’s it goin’?”

"Same old, just keeping busy.”

Both men shook hands. “This is my buddy Joe. We’ll have burgers in a few, but we’ll start with beers.”

Joe, who had briefly wondered what stories the dollar bills and Tavern Notes pinned to the wooden beams at the ceiling were telling, smiled at Hank and shook his hand, too. Looking around, he noticed that no patron seemed to wear smart glasses or even have their phones on the tables.

David pointed at the array of handwritten beer paddles hanging on the wooden panels behind the bar. “We take two Ken Browns. Can we take them out to the backyard?”

“Sure. It’s still open.”

Joe and David sat at a metal table a few yards away from the porch that was bustling with patrons. Above the table, a large tree branched out, adorned with small, twinkling lights that provided a cozy glow.

David looked up from the laptop where he had set up a connection that bounced around the globe to cover their tracks. “You ready to talk to Emmy?”

“Yeah, let’s go.”

Joe's face brightened, seeing Emily on the screen. “Thank God, you’re safe,” she said, smiling at them.

“How about you, Emmy? How are you holding up?” Joe asked.

Emily hesitated a second. “I’m good, and I think I found something about the guys who were trying to kidnap you… You know, Joe, it’s the first time I remember you asking me how I feel...”

Joe froze, then blinked.

“Okay, kids, that’s wonderful and such, but maybe we could focus on the issues at hand now? I don’t want to sound harsh, but first things first, right?”

Emily should have been annoyed by David’s remarks, but she was happy that he steered them back on track.

“You’re right, Dave. I’m sorry, Joe. So, first things: Have you made any progress with the killing cars?”

“Actually, I have, and that’s one of the reasons we’re calling. The short version: Jason Bolt built a backdoor into his AI chips. His highly theoretical swarming technology is actually hidden in the latest chipsets, enabling the Georgetown car rampage.”

“Joe, if that is true, this is…” Emily stopped as the implications hit her.

“The ultimate nightmare for a society that runs on artificial intelligence,” David completed the sentence.

“Fuck,” Emily said, the color completely drained from her face. “This also means that nearly every important system could be compromised by now. If this goes public…”

“It just can’t,” Joe butted in. “It would cause the biggest panic ever.”

“There’s truth,” David added. “And it looks like Bolt used this technology to kill one guy and let the autonomous cars butcher everybody else just to cover it up.”

“You need to speak with Alex Mercer, one of the FBI agents. He seems open to the idea that you’re not responsible for Georgetown, Joe. He also said that the FBI would likely rather kill you than catch you to close the case quickly.”

“Did you speak with Mercer again? Did you get any other information? You mentioned the kidnappers?” David asked and frowned.

“Yes, he contacted me right after you left. He told me that the kidnappers’ team leader was a guy called Brennan. They are Marines, Special Operators. Mercer served with Brennan under General Richard Clayton.”

"Who the heck is Clayton?" Joe asked, feeling lost in the conversation.

“Clayton is Brennan’s boss and has likely ordered your kidnapping. What I found online were rumors that his daughter, who was also a Marine, had been killed by U.S. autonomous drones a year ago.”

“And Clayton thinks that I have also killed his daughter, or what?” Joe was visibly stirred up.

“Again, Joe, it would be best to talk to Alex Mercer. He also knows Clayton,” Emily pleaded with Joe.

“So he can shoot me on sight and get a medal both from the FBI and that Marine general? No fucking way!”

“Honestly, I think he is our best chance to save your neck,” David said, placing his hand on Joe’s shoulder. “And we need any help we can get to stop Bolt, this insane motherfucker.”

Joe sat with his fists clenched so tight that his knuckles had turned white. He was breathing heavily and had his eyes closed. He heard Emily’s voice from the laptop: “Please, Joe. Trust me. Trust us. We need to stop this before it totally spins out of control!”

In the silence that seemed to stretch forever, Emily’s phone pinged with a breaking news alert. After glancing at the message, her eyes went wide.

“Oh God, Joe has just been officially named as the terrorist responsible for the murders in Georgetown!”

“Fuck! Emmy, we need to go right now! Contact Mercer and tell him we’re ready to meet him at my cabin ASAP.”

David slammed the laptop shut and shook Joe. “Come on, Joe, go!”

Dragging Joe behind him, David noticed commotion inside the tavern.

34. Chow

Captain Luke Brennan was getting frustrated. Of course, it was part of a Marine’s life, as it was for every soldier, to spend time on tasks with rather dubious outcomes. But he felt that he was out of his depth here. A seasoned operator, highly trained and hardened in combat, he was chasing professors through the streets of Boston and beyond, which, in the latter case, turned out to be a wild goose chase.

“Sixteen years in the Corps, and now I’m playing hide and seek with some eggheads,” he thought while gritting his teeth.

They had followed the signal of their tracker along Interstate 95 up to Houlton and, after crossing the Canadian border into New Brunswick, to a diner in Woodstock, where the driver took a break. But it turned out that the car wasn’t Donnelly’s pickup, and the driver was none of their targets.

Brennan had looked for himself at the truck and quickly discovered a metal box with two trackers attached to it in the loading area. He quickly removed both devices as it was clear that the professor had duped them like amateurs.

Back at their SUV, he had handed the devices over to Mendez, who gave them a good look. “That one ain’t ours, boss,”

“No kidding, Mendez. Disable it, will you? We will check it later on base. Maybe we will get some intel on who is also tracking Donnelly.”

With that, they turned around and made their way back to the U.S. General Clayton wasn’t too thrilled about the result of their trip either, which didn’t improve Brennan’s mood in the slightest.

It was getting dark, and the last time the team had something to eat except energy bars and Kentone shots was many hours ago. Brennan knew that the situation also grated on the nerves of his Marines, so getting some quality grub was the obvious solution.

“Mendez, we’re taking a break; find some chow. Any good around here?”

Mendez looked up the diners and pubs on the tablet. “Several options, Cap. Either lobster rolls or hamburgers seem to be the popular around here.”

Brennan peered at the tablet and pointed to the image of a rusted anchor in a backyard. “Seems to be fitting for a bunch of hungry jarheads. We take this one.”

Twenty minutes later, their black SUV was parked on the far side of the parking lot, filled with pickups and a few family cars.

Walking up the stone steps to the tavern, Marty Decker wistfully pointed to the building at the right. “They’re brewing their own beer here.”

“Hold your horses, Three. We’re keeping it dry—no beers while on the clock. Stay sharp, stay frosty.”

After stepping through the door, Brennan scanned the room for potential threats. He did not expect as much, but it was a deeply ingrained habit. The patrons were eclectic, just like the cars outside had indicated. He counted sixteen military-age males, but all seemed to mind their own business, nursing beers, and burgers.

The air was warm and smelled of savory fried food. The music, the laughter, and the dim light gave the tavern a rustic but noisy charm.

They found a corner table and settled in. Every operative turned their chair slightly to make sure their position was covered.

Luke Brennan looked at the bar, where a healthy-looking man in his sixties tended to the beers that were ordered freely, and noticed the dollar notes pinned to the wooden ceiling. He had seen strange customs around the world, and the U.S. had its fair share of them. Looking around, he felt like a stranger himself in his own country.

Brennan was thankful for being pulled out of his reverie when a waitress with auburn hair pulled into a ponytail, and a glint in her green eyes showed up to take their orders. So far, the tavern hasn’t disappointed them.

"What can I get you, boys?" the waitress asked, her smile faltering just a bit as she caught Brennan’s stern expression. After scribbling the orders on the small pad, she returned to the bar, Hanson’s eyes glued on her swinging hips.

Mendez kept an eye on the tablet and immediately saw the breaking news update on the screen. He tapped the message and jabbed his elbow in Brennan’s side when he saw what it was about. “Uhh, the manhunt has officially started, boss. Look, Hartman is wanted for the killings in Georgetown by the FBI.”

“Plastering his face all over social media ain’t making anything easier,” Brennan sighed.

“Decker, go check on our ride. We need to be ready to roll on short notice,” he added.

“What about my cheeseburger?” Decker mockingly scowled while getting up.

“Suck it up, Marine. We’ll make this one to-go for you; now move your lazy ass.”

As Decker walked to the door, Brennan noticed the barkeep holding up a phone and speaking with the waitress, who gestured at the screen. As the barkeep’s eyes went to the side, Brennan followed his gaze, which landed on the door to the outdoor area.

His eyes narrowed. Something was off here. He could feel it in his gut. It was the kind of tension that built up before the shit hit the fan.

“What the fuck is going on here?” Brennan asked as he got up and saw that the man behind the bar was now looking directly at him. The realization hit him like a hammer.

“Oh, shit. It’s Hartman. On me, move, move, move!” Brennan barked at his marines, who jumped up, sending chairs toppling down.

The life music suddenly stopped. While the families were startled, mothers pulling their children out of harm’s way, three of the sturdier-built local men sitting at the bar got up, moved in their direction, and blocked their path. “What’s wrong with you punks?” A muscular man with short-cropped hair held up his hand.

“Out of the way, motherfuckers!” Brennan pulled his Glock and shouldered through the Mainers to the door, his team following him.

When they spilled out into the backyard, there were only empty seats. Turning back to the tavern, Brennan saw that the locals were moving cautiously after them, the barkeep now sporting a Remington pump gun.

“To the car, double time!” Brennan ordered his team.

Brennan’s earpiece crackled to life while they ran around the brewery building.

“One, contact with Hartman! Should I pursue?” Decker asked.

“Wait one sec, we need to exfill! Fucking Mainiacs.”

Turning into the parking lot, he saw their SUV in the driveway, engine idling.

The doors flew open, and the Spartan operatives slid into their seats while Decker hit the gas, turning in the direction Donnelly and Hartman had taken just a minute ago.

Looking back, Brennan saw that the tavern patrons had decided to return to their beers rather than pursue them. One problem less.

Ahead, the taillights of Donnelly’s pickup truck appeared. “Fall back, Decker. We make it smooth this time. Chances are, they haven’t noticed us. Let’s not lose them.”

After a few miles, the pickup turned onto a dirt road. “Go on, Three, just after the road, then lights out. From here, we’ll stalk them.” Brennan smiled. It was hunting time.

44. Insights

“There are so many unknowns. It’s impossible to foresee what will happen if we go after Bolt,” Joe Hartman summarized after Alex Mercer and Captain Steven Monroe had updated him, Emily Stone, and David Donnelly about the situation.

“In my experience, if the waters are too muddy, fortune favors the bold,” Monroe said, earning bewildered looks.

“Yeah, let’s hope not,” David said, clapping the Marine’s shoulder.

“Sorry, no pun intended,” Monroe added quickly, with a shrug.

A sudden, firm knock on the door broke the uncomfortable silence.

“Come!” Monroe answered. Enrique Mendez entered and saluted. “Captain! Sergeant Mendez reporting with the requested items.”

Monroe returned the salute and took the day pack from the operative in civilian clothes. “Thank you, Sergeant. Dismissed.”

“I believe that’s for you, Alex,” Monroe handed the bag to Mercer after Mendez had left.

“I owe you one, Jake,” Mercer muttered as he took out the two evidence bags and placed them on the table.

“Okay, so these are the devices that Gideon Herzog, Victim One, had with him in Georgetown,” he explained.

“They won’t be much use then,” David said, eying the broken tablet. “The police used an EMP grenade to stop the cars, likely frying every circuit.”

“You can probably hear the sand trickling in the former silicon chips after being hit with that much energy,” he added, looking at Emily, who turned the bag with the memory pack in her hands.

“Do you keep your evidence in cold storage, Mercer?” she asked irritably. “If not, there’s something weird about this one.”

Mercer took it from her and whistled. “That’s weird, alright. Professors?”

Joe stepped forward and grabbed the bag. “Let’s find out,” he said, ripping the bag open while Emily stepped back.

He placed his hand on the small rectangular device, which looked identical to the one the FBI had given him two days ago.

“Some super-conductivity disperses the heat from your hand so fast that it remains cold to the touch. That’s definitely not the standard casing for a fifty-buck storage device.”

David eagerly gestured for Joe to hand over the package. “Yeah, that could be the effect of a nano-coating, shielding the contents from electromagnetic waves. Nanotechnology can make the casing extremely durable and resilient against heat and mechanical stress. I mean, look, it doesn’t even have a scratch,” David said as he held it next to the broken tablet.

“NEST,” Monroe said.

Joe turned to him. “Beg your pardon?”

“Nano-Enhanced Shielding Technology,” the Captain explained, “is a DARPA project. It’s primarily used for camouflage and scattering RADAR and LIDAR scans, but it’s also extremely durable and lightweight. An Israeli company won the competition, which caused some outrage in the American defense community.”

David smiled to himself and nodded. “Great engineering.”

“That’s very interesting, but what does it mean for our operation?” Mercer asked impatiently.

“That it’s immune against EMPs,” Emily rolled her eyes.

Twenty minutes later, the mood had darkened again. The group watched with growing desperation as Joe’s and David’s futile attempts to find anything on the device continued.

Captain Monroe looked up at the analog clock over the room’s door. “It’s literally five before twelve, guys. The General will send a team after Bolt at noon, and they won’t be considerate.”

“Yeah, tell me about it,” Joe said without looking up from the screen.

“Not Brennan’s nice guys, Hartman. The shoot first, ask later branch, if you get my drift.”

“Doesn’t bother me, as long as the fucker gets what he deserves,” David replied, his eyes glued on the screen.

“Remember the discussion we had about unknowns? We don’t know how Bolt controls the back door and if there are contingencies if something happens to him. Like somebody else hitting the red button,” Emily said louder than she had planned.

She turned to Monroe and Mercer. “When they’re in the tunnel, they don’t care about anything.”

“Come again?” Monroe asked.

“They’re spaced out. Focused on programming stuff,” Emily explained.

“Why would he bring an empty memory pack to your meeting? With a super advanced hi-tech casing. It doesn’t make sense,” Mercer said.

“But he wouldn’t want to make it obvious either. Herzog must have been aware of the danger he was in. So something is hidden in there that he needed to be protected,” Emily said.

Monroe’s eyes rested on the broken tablet. “Maybe some kind of biometrical lock? Face recognition, fingerprint?”

“That would be a dead end, quite literally,” Mercer remarked dryly. “Herzog was severely disfigured, like most of the victims. The forensics had to run DNA tests on many of the deceased to identify them.”

Joe looked up from the screen. “DNA? Maybe a DNA lock. It’s expensive, but sequencing chips are small and fast enough. And whoever built this memory pack went to lengths to make it as safe as possible.”

“But where do we get Herzog’s DNA? Break into the coroner’s office?” Emily asked, looking at Joe.

“And it’s just a hypothesis, mind you,” Monroe added. “We’re running out of time.”

His tablet chimed, and he tapped the notification. “A team is on the way to Bolt’s headquarters now. ETA is 30 minutes.”

“This is going to be messy,” Mercer said, walking over to the small table with refreshments. “Coffee, anybody?”

“Why do I feel that you would rather be with the team after Bolt than here with us?” David asked.

“You’re not wrong. Sometimes, the simple solutions are the most effective ones. Taking down Bolt looks pretty straightforward.” Alex took a sip of the burnt coffee.

“Have you tried turning it off and on again?” he asked, which earned him a frown from Joe. “Seriously, can this be reset, maybe?”

David unplugged the device and turned it around. “Don’t see no switch here, Mercer. The device is shielded and hardened. The port is likely decoupled.” For emphasis, he hit the edge of the desk a few times with the memory pack.

“It’s inert. It’s just a brick of nano-coated emptiness,” Donnelly finally said, dropping the device back on the table.

Joe watched the outburst with fascination. “Maybe that’s the whole point of it. Something is missing.”

“Sorry, I’m not following,” David raised an eyebrow.

Joe took the shattered tablet and opened the evidence bag, carefully lifting it out. “Let’s assume for a moment that Herzog had access to the same technology as Bolt. An unknown mechanism for transmitting data between devices, undetectable by conventional scanners. What if this isn’t a shielding but a communications array made of a metamaterial?”

“Meta… what?” Monroe asked.

“A special antenna,” Emily answered, quoting an article she wrote a year ago about the technology.

David looked in horror at the device he had maltreated while Joe plugged it back into their computer.

“What if Herzog stashed the info that only a special device could access it? So it’s like a super fancy WiFi dongle or a modem for the swarming protocol, disguised as a memory pack?”

He held it over the tablet, moving it back and forth until a soft green glow signaled the memory pack-turned-modem had returned to life.

“Wow,” Joe muttered as his fingers moved fast over the keyboard, “we’re in.”

The group erupted into a small celebration, with Mercer and Monroe high-fiving and Emily hugging David. But not for long.

“Stop it! We need to stop it!” Joe suddenly yelled. “Monroe, we need to stop your team. Now! Just do it!”

The captain reacted quickly, years of military drills showing their effect. Quickly pulling out his phone, he tapped a button. "Abort the mission. I repeat, abort, abort, abort!”

50. Assault

Joe Hartman stood on the Hilton’s balcony and breathed heavily. He had entered the hotel straight through the lobby. The spacious ceiling featured a series of undulating curves, subtly illuminated by recessed lighting. Joe tried to smile at the receptionists without moving too many muscles in his abused face. It felt like an eternity for the elevator doors to close.

When he finally stepped out again, he was beginning to feel better. He had encountered no security at all, and it seemed the changes to his face had been enough to fool the facial recognition. No alarm had been raised so far.

“Everything’s going too smoothly,” he thought when he stepped out on the balcony where the skywalk connected to the building. Squinting his eyes in the evening sun, he read the sign posted to the gate. It announced that the bridge was closed for the day, with its gate locked.

“Fuck,” Joe said as he took a closer look. A mesh enclosed the walkway, so there was no way to get onto it, even if he managed to get around the full-sized gate. He looked down fifty-five feet to the street level, and everything started to spin. Lightheadedly, he closed his eyes and tried to breathe deeply. He took a step back.

Joe looked at his watch. Five minutes had passed, and Mercer, Emily, and David would have started to engage the security guards at the loading bay.

Sweat started to run down his face, his heart racing.

The bridge was a highly engineered framework with numerous steel beams and girders arranged in a crisscross pattern. Thin steel mesh covered the walkway’s top. A strip on the sides, which looked sturdier, was like a screen to protect pedestrians from sun and rain.

Joe shook his head vigorously and turned around. This was impossible. He would need to go back down and find another way in. He felt the heavy M-84 grenades in his bag, tracing the holes in their cylindrical steel bodies with his sweaty fingers. A police siren was wailing nearby.

“Fuck, Fuck, Fuck!”

He rubbed his hands on his pants and looked around. Thankfully, he was still alone on the balcony. He went back to the skywalk and touched the white steel beams.

Tentatively, he hoisted himself on one of the lower beams. It felt like an eternity, but he climbed up to the small roof step after step.

Finally, he squatted on the first steel panel, which seemed even more flimsy than from below, creaking under his weight.

“Don’t look down, don’t look down, don’t look down,” he muttered.

“Hey! Stop!” Joe heard somebody yelling from the balcony.

Adrenalin surging through his system, Joe got up and started moving. Behind him, he heard a second voice calling for the hotel’s security.

He was scrambling now, his shoes barely gripping the slick steel panels. The grenades were clanging together as the bag began to swing wildly. His vision was reduced to a tunnel, focusing on the end of the sixty-foot-long bridge. Finally, he jumped down on the Convention Center’s balcony, hitting it hard.

But that didn’t stop Joe Hartman. He felt more alive than ever before. He dashed through the door and nearly ran over a kid with dyed hair and an oversized neon-colored sweater who was returning from the restrooms.

The security on the door, a burly man in black cargo pants and a hoodie with Bolt Industry’s logo emblazoned on the chest, held out a hand.

“Easy, pal!”

He looked Joe up and down, who was drenched in sweat, then at the kid in the neon sweater.

Joe took a deep breath, trying to steady his trembling hands and force a semblance of calm into his voice. “Look, this is going to be the keynote people will talk about in the years to come,” Joe panted, his eyes pleading, his voice strained with urgency and desperation.

The kid next to him nodded enthusiastically.

In a moment of leniency that the security guard would regret dearly in the next minutes, he stepped aside and opened the large door to the ballroom.

“You Bolt fanboys are just nuts,” he uttered under his breath.

When Jason Bolt entered the ballroom, music pumping, the crowd roared. Like a rock concert or a championship box fight, although a bit nerdy if you looked closely enough. He narrowly passed Joe Hartman, who stood at the back of the 40,000-square-foot room, on his way to the stage. His entrance was displayed on the large holographic screens lining the front wall.

Joe felt hate welling up in him, like never before. This man had tried to kill him and his friends, perverted everything he believed in, and was about to plunge the world into chaos. He tightly clenched one of the grenades that featured a solid hex socket at the bottom. Joe had never been a violent man, but he felt the urge to jump at Bolt and wallop him with the flashbang.

Of course, he wouldn’t get far, with Bolt being protected by the FBI agents who walked around him in a diamond formation, scanning the crowd for threats. And not to forget the damn implant.

No, he would have to focus on the task. He would wait until Bolt arrived at the stage before he could explode the stun grenades; the service elevator down to the loading bay was right behind the large screens. Bolt was running late, a calculated move to raise the suspense in the room and on the screens. Telling from the cheering 4,000 or so people in the audience, it seemed to work well.

Nobody was paying attention to him. Joe fumbled slightly with the first flashbang, his hands shaking as he recalled Mercer’s brief instructions. He took a deep breath, steeling himself before tossing it into the room.

Jake Lin kept an eye out for anything suspicious as they weaved through the crowd. People were getting out of their seats and clapping along to the powerful music. From a security standpoint, this was a nightmare. Although Bolt’s security lined the way up to the stage, Jason high-fived one of his screaming fans every now and then and came dangerously close to the masses.

The crowd control algorithms stopped working altogether, overwhelmed by the rambunctious audience. The moment he was eye-clicking away the notification on his smart glasses, he had an uncanny feeling, like his unconsciousness had registered something, but he couldn’t put his finger on it. Something wasn’t right. But the hustle and bustle around him and the steady movement towards the stage made it impossible for Jake to turn back and check out what had irritated him.

Probably someone in the crowd, but the facial recognition didn’t alert him. There was no time for brooding, so he focused again on his charge.

Alex Mercer had positioned himself next to the service elevator and noticed two guards wearing the same high-visibility vest as the one he had taken from the kid in the security station. They didn’t look overly concerned as they strolled over to the station, probably doing a routine check.

Mercer cursed. What was Hartman doing? They couldn’t hold their position much longer, and the two guys were an imminent threat. Mercer tensed and reached instinctively for his gun but stopped short. Shooting them was out of the question. Too much noise from a tactical point of view. And they were just doing their job. Killing innocents didn’t sit right with Mercer. Never had.

But he couldn’t leave his position either. If Hartman finally exploded the stun grenades, things would move fast, and they wouldn’t get a second chance at Bolt.

As the two reached the station’s door, Mercer couldn’t do much more than hope that David Donnelly, waiting inside, would know what to do.

Jason Bolt enjoyed every second of his glorious entrance to the ballroom. The audience’s emotions carried him up to the lectern. When the media called him “the tsar of artificial intelligence” in a report before the developer conference, he thought that was selling him short. Things didn’t turn out well for the last tsar, either.

No, he would unleash artificial intelligence, making it omnipresent and omniscient, continuously learning and growing without petty restrictions. All centered around his beautiful mind. The world would become Jason’s. Soon, very soon, he could let go of any restraint. He could already feel the data streams all around him, like glittering silver strands weaving through the air.

He flashed a bright smile at the camera drone before suddenly the room was engulfed in blinding light and the deafening sound of explosions. Panic erupted around him, and people screamed and ran for the doors.

“Move, move, move,” he heard a distant voice, disoriented from the impact of the M-84 stun grenades that Joe had thrown in his direction. Arms grabbed him, and he was dragged forward. Klaxons blared amidst the chaos, the sprinkler system releasing a steady stream of water. The screens on the walls flickered and went black. The air was thick with smoke, carrying the strong odors of sulfur and burning chemicals. His bodyguards violently shoved through the crowd, keeping their principal in the center, to the service elevator.

Travis Riggs, the special agent in charge, pressed his badge against the elevator panel, which flashed a red “Out of Order.” A moment later, the door opened, accepting the agent’s override, and the group piled in.

Riggs looked around as the doors closed and the elevator started to move down to the loading bay, doing a quick roll call. “Where’s Lin?” he asked, his ears still ringing from the explosion.